<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The booke of thrift, containing a perfite order, and right methode to profite lands, and other things belonging to husbandry. ; Newly Englished, and set out by I.B. gentleman of Caen in France.</title>
            <author>Henley, Walter de, fl. 1250.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00849</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25007.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124440</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">57402345</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 57402345</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181146</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00849)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181146)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2171:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The booke of thrift, containing a perfite order, and right methode to profite lands, and other things belonging to husbandry. ; Newly Englished, and set out by I.B. gentleman of Caen in France.</title>
                  <author>Henley, Walter de, fl. 1250.</author>
                  <author>Bellot, Jacques.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 18 [i.e. 54] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Initials.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Walter de Henley by STC (2nd ed.) and CDNB.</note>
                  <note>Dedication ascribed by "Iames Bellot Gentleman of Caen in Normandy".</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A³ B-D⁸ E³.</note>
                  <note>Pages numbered on recto only, with numerous errors in numbering; leaves 25, 26, 27 are numbred 22, 23, 18, respectively.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Glasgow. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Agriculture --  Economic aspects --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Farm management --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:181146:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Booke of Thrift, <hi>containing a perfite order,</hi> and right methode to profite lands, and other things belonging to Husbandry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Newly Engliſhed, and ſet <hi>out by I. B. Gentleman of Caen,</hi>
               </hi> in France.</p>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed by Iohn Wolfe.</hi> 1589.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:181146:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:181146:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT Honorable Sir Francis</hi> Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham Knight, Chauncellor of <hi>Lancaſter, firſt Secretary of eſtate to</hi> the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, and one of her Maieſties moſt Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable priuie Counſell, Iames Bellot Gentleman of Caen in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy, wiſheth health.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>being not long agone in a friends houſe of mine, he ſhewed me an old Booke of Parchment, in a writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:181146:3"/> hand, entreating of ſundry matters, and in ſundry languages: The which, when I had ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, I fell (by chaunce) vppon a little Treatiſe of Huſbandrye and plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, written in old French, ſo ill ſet together, and ſo ſtraungely painted, that I had much a doo before I could reape any thing of it: but finally, it was gods will (after I had long mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon it) to ſhewe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee the meaning of the ſame: And finding it a worke right worthie to be
<pb facs="tcp:181146:3"/> put in the handes of the publike, (becauſe it entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of publike affaires) I thought good, yea moſt reaſonable, to commit it firſt into your lerned ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, to the ende that vnder the protection of your authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, it might walke in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſafetie. Therefore, I beſeech your Honour moſt humbly, to receiue it accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably, &amp; to looke on it with ſo bountifull an eye, that it may be the bolder to ſhew it ſelfe: not only in Engliſh through all this Realme, but alſo in other langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:181146:4"/> throughout all inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted countries: and ſo, your Honour ſhall graft within me a moſt entire, and moſt pure affection to praie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God (as yet at this time I do pray) to grant you (in health, and long time) an encreaſe of all Honorable eſtates, with true &amp; eternal felicitie.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:181146:4"/>
            <head>An account for <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt he that ſhal ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der account, ought to ſweare that he ſhall render a true accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and ſhall charge him ſelfe with that, that he hath receyued of the Lords goods, &amp; that he hath not put in his ſcrole by his good will, but that which he hath lawfully ſpent about the Lords profit. And the clearke ought to ſweare, that he hath truely put in his account, that which he iudgeth his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to haue receiued of the goods of the Lord, and hath imployed nothing but that which hee knoweth to bee for the Lords profite. And then if he haue at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times rendred the like account: It ought be looked vnto how it is diuided, and if he be found in a rerage of money, or of corne, or of both, or of any other thing, let him caſt vp all to the iuſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of money, to charge therewith his account, at the beginning of his ſcrole, and to ſet it downe after the accounts
<pb facs="tcp:181146:5"/> of other rents receiued for the Lorde, and of all other things whereof neuer a penie may bee leuied, and to charge the account thereof, and to employ it at the ende in a great ſumme, and after to go to the expenſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the coſt for carts, it is good for the ſmith to take a note, for to finde out what is néedful to haue of iron, and of ſtéele for the ploughes, and ſhooe the horſes and all other their affayres, and to put that which may be behoouefull to be done, and is accuſtomed to be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of allowance in the countrey: and the ſame man ſhall ſée, if within the manor there is growing any great wood, or great timber, or timber that a man may gather thereof axeltrées, naues, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſarie things to be felled, aſwel for carts as for ploughs, ſo taking them a man may ſpare money. And for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerplus, which is not there to be had, and neceſſarie for him to buy, let it bee allowed vnto him. And it will bee good for him to haue both Carters &amp; plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men which can worke all the timber of the carwood, the more are theſe two
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:181146:5"/> ſorts of ſeruants to bee enterteyned. The ſayde man ſhall ſée at the ende of the yéere, all the ſmal neceſſarie things, all the prouiſions, all the yron, and all thoſe things which in the manour doe remaine little and ſmall, and to write after in the other yéere, what thing it behoued him neceſſarily to buy, and to allow the ſame, and the ouerplus lay vp ſafely. The Prouoſt ought to cauſe to be gathered all the pilles of the trées to make cordes, for that, that hee ſhall néede of, and he muſt cauſe, to ſow with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the yard, hempe to make cordes for the carts, as haltars and other neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie things, &amp; the making of them muſt be allowed vnto him, if there be none of the houſhold that can make them. Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of houſes, walles, hedges and dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches if néede be, ought to be allowed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto reaſon: yet the prouoſt muſt not ſell, buy, receyue, nor deliuer any thing except by tally, or by good te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie And the bailey muſt make all the ſeruants of the houſe, when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from labour, to labour about the yard, to threſh corne, or to make wals,
<pb facs="tcp:181146:6"/> ditches, hedges, or other neceſſarie workes about the houſe, for the ſparing of money, and if there be any ſeruant of the houſe that can doe the worke: he muſt therefore allowe him more then any other: if he cauſe him to make that worke, and allow another to worke in his ſtead. The ſtewards or the bailies, ſhall ſée all the buyings, and all the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings which the baily or prouoſt ſhall make, for to ouerſée that they bee well done, and to the profit of the Lord. And the ſteward and baylies which do kéepe the court, incontinent after the ſaide buying, ought to render their ſcroles at the Lordes court, or to the auditors of the court, that they may charge by their ſcroles the prouoſts, and baylies which doe remaine accomptable of the profits of the yard for the whole yeare. And the prouoſt muſt make account of the iſſue of the Mares of the yarde, that is to wit, for each Mare a Colt by the yeare, and if there bee any that haue neuer a Colt, let it be inquired of, whether it be through ill regarde, or by want of good kéeping, or through ouer much trauell,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:181146:6"/> or by default of a ſtallion, or that ſhe be barren and bringeth no coltes, that hee may haue her chaunged for another in time: and it makes no matter whether he be in like maner charged of the iſſue or of the value of the ſame. And if there be any horſe, or other beaſt dead, let it be inquired whether it bee through the default of the kéeper, or of the baylie, or of the prouoſt, who might haue well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it, or to haue imployed ſome helpe about it, and did it not if they could, let them beare the loſſe thereof vpon their owne goods. And if they doe die by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, that it be not by their fault, as of the Morien, and any other diſeaſes vpon beaſts, let the prouoſt be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the carkaſſes, and of the ſkins, and of the fleſh, and the iſſues, and put them in the profite of the Lord, and let him imploy that, that he ſhall know or be able to prooue. And if there be anie thing loſt in the yard, or without, or ſtollen away, the which be it quicke or dead, either little or great, whereby the Lord may haue any maner of loſſe, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by burning, or by any other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb facs="tcp:181146:7"/> the Lorde muſt charge the pro uſt therewith, and the prouoſt muſt charge thoſe of the yarde which are guiltie thereof. And it is to be knowen, that all the ſeruants of the yarde, men and women muſt be attendant on the prouoſt, becauſe that the prouoſt muſt anſwere for all their actions, and the prouoſt ought to bring into the Court thoſe for whom he wil anſwer for their déedes. And the ſteward muſt ſée that the prouoſt enter good pledges for all thoſe of the yarde which are placed by the prouoſt: and if the Lord receyue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny domages by the prouoſt, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoſt hath not wherewithall he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the domages, all them of the town which haue choſen him, ſhall anſwere the ſurpluſſage for him, of that, that he ſhall not bee able to pay. And if the Lord doth place there a ponder, a field-kéeper, or a granger, or any other what ſoeuer he be, and the Lord doe receiue any damage by the fault of them the which hee ſhall haue there placed, the Lord ought to take his mends of them, becauſe hee placed them, and not of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:181146:7"/> his prouoſt. It is to be vnderſtood, that manours that are gouerned by baylies, where there is no prouoſt, but the bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly who anſwereth for the manour that the ſayd bayly ſhall render account, as the prouoſt ſhall and all the other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ought to anſwere to him for all thinges, without any alteration or change of wordes as vnto the prouoſt. And thoſe which doe holde in villenage of any maner, ought to chooſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoſt ſuch as they will bee anſwerable for, for if the Lord doth receyue any do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage by default of the prouoſt, and he hath not wherewithal to ſatiſfie it, they ſhall pay for him the ſurpluſſage which he can not pay.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An anſwere of the ſeedes that muſt be ſowen.</head>
               <p>AL the land muſt be meaſured each one by it ſelfe, and euery holding of the field named by their names, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery medowe by it ſelfe, and euery pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, euery wood, and euery heath, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie, moore and mariſh alſo by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and all by the pearch of ſixtéene
<pb facs="tcp:181146:8"/> foote and a halfe, becauſe it is eaſie for one to meaſure the lande there by the pole of ſixtéene foote and a halfe. They doe ſowe in many places foure acres with one quarter, and in many other places, it is required to haue one quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and a halfe to ſowe fiue acres of wheate, and of rie, and of beanes, and of peaſon, and two acres with one quarter of barley, and of otes. But becauſe that ſome will bee ſowen thicker then the other, the partie ought to meaſure in each manor euery acre by the corne, and ſée howe much a man may ſowe of each kind of corne vpon one meaſure, then may you alwayes bee certaine of your ſowing. And becauſe that a man ſoweth barley vpon a wheate field, and beanes, and peaſon, and lentiles amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ngſt the otes, the partie ought to name each land which is ſowen in barley amongſt the wheate, and each land of other corne which is ſowen, amongſt the otes. And there where the fieldes are diuided in two, the winterage or wintercorne, and the tramis (otherwayes common barley) are ſowen in one and the ſame
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:181146:8"/> field. Therefore he muſt anſwere that of each land, what land is ſowen of one kinde of corne, and which of another. And if there be any incloſure, he muſt ſée what land he taketh in the incloſure and with what corne hee ſoweth each land, and the ſame ſéede hee muſt ſcore by it ſelfe out of the other graine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How a man ought to alow, or hire the harueſt men in harueſt time, and in time of making of hay.</head>
               <p>YOu may well haue your lands wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for a penie an acre, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre of medow mowed for foure pence, and the acre of lande in the valley for thrée pence halfepenie, and take vppe and ſtubbe the acre for thrée halfpence, and to take vp and ſtubbe the acre of medow in the valley, for one penie far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: and you ought well to knowe, that fiue men may well reape and tie two acres by the day of each kinde of corne, ſome more, ſome leſſe. And where euery one taketh two pence by the day,
<pb facs="tcp:181146:9"/> yet you ought to giue fiue pence for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery acre, and vnto many more. And when the foure do take thrée halfpence a péece, by day, and the fift becauſe he is a tier, two pence a day, you ought then to giue for each acre foure pence. And becauſe that in many countreys they cannot reape by the acre, yet may a man know by the reapers, and by the dayes, that which they doe, ſo that you kéepe the reapers by the lands: to wit, fiue men or women the which you pleaſe, fiue men doe make one land, and fiue &amp; twentie men do make fiue lands: and fiue and twentie men may reape and tie ten acres by the day in ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble weather, and in ten dayes an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred acres, and in twentie dayes two hundred acres by fiue ſcore to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. Then you ſhall ſée how many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres hee hath to reape, in all, and you ſhall ſée whether they agrée with the dayes, and then ſhall you allow them: And if they doe recken more dayes then it behoueth according vnto the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, you ought not to allowe it them, for it is their fault that haue not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:181146:9"/> them, and cauſed them to worke ſo well as they ſhould.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Howe landes ought to be meaſured.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd becauſe the acres are not all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, for in ſome countreys they doe meaſure by the pole of eightéene foote, and in ſome countreyes by the pole of twentie foote, and in ſome countreys by the pole of foure and twentie foote: and you muſt knowe, that the acre that is meaſured by the pole of eightéene foote, maketh an acre and a roode and the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenth part of a roode, of the pole of ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téene foote, and foure acres make fiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres, and the fourth part of a roode, and eight acres, do make twelue acres and a halfe roode, and ſixtéene acres make twentie acres and one roode. And the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre which is meaſured by the pole of twentie foote, maketh an acre and a halfe, and the fourth part of a roode, of the pole of ſixtéene foote, and foure acres doe make ſixe acres and one roode, and eight acres make twelue acres and a
<pb facs="tcp:181146:10"/> halfe, and ſixtéene acres both make fiue and twentie acres: and the acre which is meaſured by the pole of two &amp; twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie foote, maketh an acre and a half and a roode and a halfe, and the ſixtenth part of a roode of the pole of ſixtéene foote, and the foure acres doe make ſeuen acres and a halfe, and the fourth part of a roode, and eight acres make fiftéene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres and halfe a roode, and ſirtéene acres doe make thirtie acres and one roode. And the acre which is meaſured by the pole of foure and twentie foote, maketh two acres and a roode of the pole of ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téene foote, and foure acres doe make nine acres.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The anſwer of the barne.</head>
               <p>OF the profits of the barne, the man ought to ſée how much of each corne he hath ſowen, and how much it doeth anſwere in profite: that is by right and by common account, barly doth anſwer at the eight graine, that is to wit for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery corne ſowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eight cornes increaſe: and the rie, at the ſeuenth corne, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:181146:10"/> beanes at the ſixth beane, and peaſon at the ſixth peaſe, and of dredges of barly, and of otes, if they be equally mingled, at the ſixth: and if there be more barley then otes, it ought to anſwer the more, and if there be leſſe barley, it muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ethe leſſe, &amp; alſo of maſline, if it be equally mingled muſt anſwere at the ſixt, and if there be more wheate then rie, it anſwereth the leſſe, &amp; the wheate muſt anſwer at the fifth corne, and the otes at the fourth. But becauſe the landes doe not anſwere ſo well in one yeare as in another, the light landes do not anſwere as the good doe: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it happeneth that the winterage taketh well, and the Lent faileth, and ſometimes the Lent taketh, and the winterage fayleth: and therefore if the land anſwereth more then it is char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the corne, the Lord looſeth it, and if it doth anſwere leſſe, of neceſſitie it behoueth him which rendereth the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, to pay it of his owne, and ſo no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can receiue damage by the account aforeſayde. And there is no perill to put men which may anſwere by the corne.
<pb facs="tcp:181146:11"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:181146:11"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:181146:12"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:181146:12"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:181146:13"/> and whoſoeuer knoweth not the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, let him place a faithfull man in whom he truſteth beſides the threſher of the barne: and it is good for him which is beſide the threſher of the barne to ſcore the increaſe of each heape in the barne by it ſelfe, for to ſée howe many quarters each heape of corne ought to render by it ſelfe. And if there be any heape without, let him cauſe it to bée meaſured by rode, and by foote in height and length, when he will cauſe it to be threſhed, and let him ſcore each heape by it ſelfe, then ſhall he be able to know as wel af each heape without, as of ache heape within the barne, both the ſtock &amp; the profite: ſo that the heapes be euery one of one height, and of one length: and if he will ſell his corne by the great, he may the better knowe howe much each heape ought to be worth, according vnto the price of the corne, if he ſelleth the corne by the great. It is good for him to ſcore, and to ſée the profite of each heape, and of each ſtacke: for the ofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he ſhall trie it, the certener he ſhall be of the profite, and of the ſtocke, be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:181146:13"/> cauſe that corne doth not anſwer euery yeare equally: and let him take héede which is with the threſher of corne, that if he doth threſh any olde corne with the new, he threſh, and ſcore it by it ſelfe out from the newe, and that the prouoſt may anſwere the ſale of the corne ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and ſée the profite euery yeare, whether it ſhall anſwer to his ſéede.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſwere of dredges.</head>
               <p>ANd if you doe make dredges, they muſt alwayes anſwere to you for nine quarters the tenth at the leaſt, and yet it is a very ſmall anſwer, but a man may bring it to this reckoning, becauſe that he may not make thereof a greater ſtore, when he putteth in greater ſtore of otes, the dredges thereof wilbe worth the leſſe, and of all the increaſe thereof the leſſe Béere ſhall be made.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The profite of the dairie, concerning the ſmall ſtore.</head>
               <p>ANd you ought to haue in each place and dyarie a man or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to kéepe
<pb facs="tcp:181146:14"/> the ſmal ſtore of the croppe, as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde. And if there be a man, yet he muſt doe all things euen ſo as if a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man were there, and ought to take the quarter of the yeare of ſixtéene wéekes for the white meate, where the other quarters are taken of twelue wéekes, and he muſt ſell all the corne, and ſhall take of the money of the dairie that is payed, to pay the woman which ſelleth it: If you do meaſure to ſell foure quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of wheate, or of rie, and ſixe quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of barley, of peaſon, beanes and minglings, you muſt allow in the ſale one halfe penie and a halfe for euery oen of them: if they be meaſured to ſale eight quarters of otes, for the ſame one penie: and the man ought alwayes to take in the quarter the fift for the full meaſure of euery kind of graine: Alſo a man ought to threſh the quarter of wheate, or of rie for two pence, and the quarter of barley, beanes and peaſon, for two pence halfepenie, and the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of otes for one penie, and to allow alwayes for euery fourth the fift for the full meaſure: and if the dairie wife take
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:181146:14"/> héede to all the ſayde ſtore which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in the yard, as to the ſwine and peacocks, and to their increaſe, and to the géeſe and to their increaſe, and to the capons, and to the cockes, and to the hennes, and to the chickens, and to the egges and their increaſe: and you ought to know that the ſowe muſt pigge two times by the yeare, and at each time ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen pigges at the leaſt, and euery gooſe muſt bring foorth fiue goſlings by the yeare, and each henne muſt lay one hundred and fiftie egges, and bréed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen chickens, whereof thrée muſt bee made capons, and if there be to many henne chickens, ſhe muſt change them for cocke chickens: ſo many as it is here found that euery henne muſt increaſe thrée capons and foure hennes by the yeare: and for fiue géeſe, it behoueth to haue one gander, and to ſeuen hennes one cocke. And each cow muſt anſwere one calfe by the yeare, and each ewe ſhéepe one lambe by the yeare: and if there be any cow or ewe ſhéepe which bringeth forth no increaſe, let him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire by whoſe default it is, either by
<pb facs="tcp:181146:15"/> the fault of the bailie, or of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoſt, or of the kéeper, through fault of good kéeping, or by want of food in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, or in winter ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or through want of a male, or if the prouoſt may haue changed it for any other in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>méet time. And if it be not found by the default of none of them, let him make a full change of the iſſue, or of the valour thereof. And alſo if none dieth by any maner of way by his default, let him be anſwerable for the quicke beaſt, or of the value thereof: and if the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour lacketh a dairie, it is alwayes good to haue a faithfull woman for the lighteſt coſtes that a man may, for to kéepe the ſmall ſtore, croppe, and all which is within the yard, and to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer all the iſſues as well of the crops, as of the dairie: to wit, of the ſowes and of their pigges, of the peacocks and of their chickens, of the géeſe and of their goſlings, of the capons and of the cocks, of the hennes and of their chickens, and of their egges, and ſhe muſt be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the halfe of the ſelling of them, as well as of the dayrie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:181146:15"/>
               <head>Anſwere of the white meate of kine.</head>
               <p>EAch cow ought to anſwere from Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmaſſe day till the firſt Kalends May, by eight and twentie wéekes, the one and the older, the account of ten pence throughout all that time, the one more, and the other leſſe. And it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to vnderſtande, that euerie cowe doth anſwere by equalitie, for the one giueth ſooner milke then the other, and the one is ſooner drie then the other, neither doe the Heyforts anſwere ſo much milke at their firſt bearing, as they doe at the other bearings after: but of thoſe of eight yeare olde, they ought to anſwere ſo much: and the next day after the firſt Kalends of May, till S. Michaels day, by foure and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wéekes, the one day ſo much as the other, and they doe make right ſkore and eight dayes, and the profite of the milke of euery Cowe, muſt be woorth during that time, thrée ſhillings and ſixe pence, &amp; all the other ſeaſon, the iſſue of the cow commeth to ten pence, &amp; by this
<pb facs="tcp:181146:16"/> account euery cow ought to anſwer iiij. ſhillings .iiij. pence, of the profite of the milke: and it is to be vnderſtood, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery cow muſt anſwer betwene the kalends of May, and Michaelmaſſe, ſix ſtones of chéeſe, and alwaies of ſix ſtones of chéeſe one ſtone of butter, and you ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies from the next day after Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſe till Saint Martins day at the leaſt, and in the other ſeaſon, after Chriſtmaſſe till Sommer time, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth more to the Lord to ſel the milke, then to ſell chéeſe: for it is more profite then to ſell a gallon of milke, then to ſel thrée gallons in Sommer, or at any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeaſon: and if you doe make chéeſe, then a gallon of milke will be no more worth then it is worth at any other ſeaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The anſwere of the whitmeate of ſheepe.</head>
               <p>EAch milked ſhéepe ought to anſwere profit of her milke, all the Sommer long, ſo long as ſhee giues milke ſixe pence: for the ſhéepe that giues milke, giues no milke after Auguſt, and no
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:181146:16"/> man doth kéepe them for to giue milke after Auguſt, becauſe that they are leſſe woorth, and are the more perillous to paſſe the Winter, and if they be ſicke, or féeble, their profite is the leſſe. And the dairie wife ought to anſwer ſo much profite of a gallon of ſhéepes milke in chéeſe and butter, as of a gallon and a halfe of cowes milke: and a gallon doth weigh ſeuen pounds: and two gallons, do weigh fouretéene pounds, and foure-pounds makes the ſtone. And it is to be knowen, that the Mare goeth fortie nine wéekes after ſhee hath bene coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, before ſhe bring forth any colt. And the Cowe from the time that ſhe hath beene couered goeth fortie wéekes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhee bring foorth any calfe. And the ſhéepe goeth xxj. wéekes from the time ſhe hath béene couered, before ſhe bring a lambe. And the ſowe goeth xv. wéekes, from the time that ſhe hath bin couered, before ſhe farow any pigs. And the ſowe farroweth her pigges fiue times in two yeares, and no more. And the gooſe bréedeth one time by the yere. And the hen hatcheth if ſhe be well
<pb facs="tcp:181146:17"/> kept, and be good two times in a yeare, but that happeneth not euery yeare: neither can euery one of them giue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, but onely according as they ſhall be well kept, anſwere they profite, either more or leſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>This husbandrie made a Knight, ſir Walter of Henley, who after ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered himſelf into the order of the Friers-preachers, &amp; did reach vnto the people, how they ought to liue wiſely and hoheſtly of their goods, and not to waſte too much before hand, leſt they ſhould want after.</head>
               <p>THe father ſate in his olde age, and ſayde to his ſonne, Faire ſonne, liue wiſely, according to God, and after the world. Towards God thinke often of the paſſion, and of the death that Ieſus Chriſt ſuffered for vs, and loue him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things, and feare him, &amp; kéepe his commandements. As touching the world, thinke yee on the whéele of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, how men haue no riches, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are on the top of the whéele, howe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:181146:17"/> by miſchance they doe fall into pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and more into afflictions: therefore I pray you to order your life according as your lands are worth, and do extend by the yeare, and no higher: If you can improue your lands to gaines, either by ſtoring or by other purueyance more then the ordinarie reuenue, kéepe the ouerplus in ſtore: for if corne faile, ſtore dyeth, or burning happeneth to come, or any other miſchance, then the ſame that you haue in ſtore will be profitable to you. If you do ſpend by the yeare the worth of your lands, &amp; any loſſe in the yeare or miſchance happen to come, you haue no recourſe to your ſtore, and let the ſtorer make no waſte, nor deſtroy his goods, as ſome men do, as thoſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which do by for twentie ſhillings, and do ſell for ten, that man is neither called nor approoued wiſe, that can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer himſelfe out of loſſe and dooth it not. You may ſée ſome men which haue landes and reuenues, and can not tell howe to liue: wherefore I will tell it you, becauſe they liue without order, or any forecaſt, or prouiſion afore hande,
<pb facs="tcp:181146:18"/> and they ſpend &amp; waſt more then their lands are worth by the yeare, and when they haue waſted their goods: then haue nothing but ſorrow in their mouthes, &amp; doe liue in anguiſh, neither can they make any ſhift for their profit. Such a man may one reproue in Engliſh thus: Whoſo ſtriketh further then his whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle wil laſt, in the ſtroke his foot he muſt ſtretch. Faire ſonne, be you wiſe in your déed, and againſt this world which is ſo miſchieuous and tickliſh, that you may want nothing, &amp; that you néed not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon any man for your reliefe. If there be any men carting in your yards, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be aduiſed by their elders, &amp; if in your iudgement you think that they be too high minded, be you aduiſed here to meaſure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you may not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended thereby, neither here nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. Be you acquainted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> honeſt perſons &amp; wiſe, &amp; you ſhal haue the loue of your neighbors: for it is ſaid in Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch: whoſoeuer hath a good neighbor, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame hath a good morning. Vſe your tongue wiſely, that you be not iuſtly reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: you ſhall diſcretly ſpend thoſe goods which God hath lent you.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:181146:18"/>
               <p>You ought to know foure things, in layings out and in expenſes: the firſt is, What yee muſt giue, how &amp; to whom, and how much you muſt giue: for the firſt, that you muſt giue before néed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it: for two ſhillings giuen then, are better accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of then twelue ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, when néede forceth you to it: for the ſecond, whether you ought to giue, or to ſpend, and to doe it willingly, then the ſame ſhall bee double rewarded vnto you, and if you do giue vnwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you ſhall léeſe all that you doe either giue or lay out: for the thirde, giue to him that may be profitable vnto you &amp; to others: for the fourth, how much you muſt giue, neither more nor leſſe, but according as the worke is, either great, or litle, that you haue to do: looke on the poore, not for the praiſes of the worlde, but for to haue the loue of God, which giueth vs all things. You ſhall enlarge your lands and tenements by your loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al men ſworn. Firſt recken your yards, gardens, doue-houſes, orchardes, what they may be worth by the yeere, beſides your prouiſion.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:181146:19"/>
               <p>Then reckon howe many acres of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow you haue, and what they be woorth by the yéere, and ſée alſo how much wood you may ſell by the year, without any waſte or deſtruction, and what the ſame may be woorth by the yeare: and what your milles: and your fiſh ponds are worth by the yeare, beſides the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion: and then reckon how many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres you haue of erable land: and how many be of them in euery field: and of frée holds, how much each of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth, and by what ſeruice: and of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie hold, how much euery one of them conteyneth, and by what ſeruices and cuſtoms or duties they be held, let them be employed and all other things wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they do profite, account what they be worth by the yeare. And by the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, you ſhall enquire howe much will ſerue to ſowe an acre of land, of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery kind of corne, and how much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions you may haue vpon euery ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: and by the allowance you ſhall know how much your bailyes muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere in their ſcrowles, beſides the ſayd alowance. So may you be able to know
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:181146:19"/> how much your lands are woorth by the yeare, and your tenements alſo, wherby you may diſpoſe of your liuing ſo as it is tolde you before, and whether your prouoſts do ſet downe in their accounts ſo much corne ſowen, vpon ſo many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres: So to the allowance, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance ſhall you finde fewer acres then they will tell you, &amp; more corne ſowen then it were néede or requiſite: for you haue at the end of the allowance with how much a man may ſowe an acre of land of all ſorts of graine. Beſides this, if néede were to beſtowe either more or leſſe coſt about the ploughes: by the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance you ſhall be certified how: I will tell it you. If your lands are diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by three, the one part to the winter, and another part in Lent, and the third part in reſting land, then is the plough nine ſcore acres. And if your landes be diuided by two, the one moitie is ſowen in winter, and in Lent: and the other moitie in reſting land, then ſhall the plough be of eight ſcore acres. Go you to the allowance, and ſée how many acres in demain land you haue, and thereby
<pb facs="tcp:181146:20"/> you may be certified as well how much the plough of eight ſcore acres hath to do, as the plough of nine ſcore acres hath to doe. I will ſhewe vnto you, that of eight ſcore acres, is fortie acres of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teredge, and fortie acres of lent, and foure ſcore acres of reſting lande: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and replough the foure ſcore acres, and then the plough ſhall goe of twelue ſcore acres. Concerning the plough of nine ſcore acres, thrée ſcore acres for winteredge, and thrée ſcore acres for lent, and thrée ſcore for reſting land, and then runne ouer and plough againe the thrée ſcore acres. Then ſhall the plough goe for twelue ſcore acres by the yeere, as the plough of eight ſcore: Some men do ſaie, that a plough cannot do ſo much by the yéere, I wil ſhew you that it may doe it: You knowe that an acre ought to bée of fortie poles in length, and foure poles in breadth, and the kinges pole is of ſixtéene foote and an halfe. Then is the acre of ſixtie ſixe foote of breadth: Now goe on forward thirtie thrée times about, and take roome of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:181146:20"/> one foote in breadth. Then is the acre otherwiſe. But goe thirtie ſixe times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout for to make the roome narrow, and when the acre is gone forwarde then you haue gone ſeauentie and two fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, which doe make ſixe leagues, that is to wit, twelue furlonges for one league: the horſe ſhall be verie poore, or the oxe either, the which in one morning cannot goe ſoftly and with a little pace the waie of thrée leagues, and to go back at noone. And by another reaſon I will ſhewe you that it may doe ſo much. You knowe that there is fiftie two weekes in one yeere: now take away eight weeks for the holy daies and other lettes, then ſhall remaine fortie foure weekes of trauayle, and in all that time the ploughe ſhall haue to doe, but the plowing of the reſting lande, and the plowing of the ſowing in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and in Lent, the dayes-worke of three roodes, and halfe a rood, and to ſtir againe one acre. Nowe ſee you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ploughe which is well kept and folowed, may not do ſo much in one day,
<pb facs="tcp:181146:21"/> and if you haue lands whereon dungue may be layd, take paines to dungue it according as the land doth require: and haue regarde to knowe whether your land be well in dungue, and whether your dungue bee well kept as it muſt, then it ſhall anſwere to the thirde part of your lands by the alowance. Be they your tenants or cuſtomers, if they doe deny cuſtoms or ſeruices by your alow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, you ſhall know the certaintie.</p>
               <p>If you be to chooſe bailifes, or ſerge, ants, chooſe them neither by kinred, nor by fauourable worde, nor by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like things, if they be not of good name, and let them be honeſt and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and ſuch as knowe the profite of the dungue. Take no corne-kéepers but of your homagers and lande-holders: and if you doe chooſe them, let them bee of your homagers chooſing: for if they treſpaſſe, you ſhall haue your remedie vpon them.</p>
               <p>At the beginning of breaking, tilling and ſowing of your lands, ſée that the bailifes and the kéepers or prouoſts, be alwayes in companie with the plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:181146:21"/> to ſée that they worke plainly, and doe well their worke, and at their iourneys ende, to ſée howe much they haue done, ſo that they may be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for all afterwards, except they can be able to ſhew certaine apparant let: and becauſe that ſeruants are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſlacke in their workes, it is néedefull to caſt ouer their fraudes. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane time it is néedefull for the kéeper to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh them euery day. On the other part, the bailife ought to looke ſo well about it, that they doe well: and if they doe not well, let them be rebuked, and corrected for it.</p>
               <p>You ſhall at the plough of oxen draw one of your horſes: for the plough of oxen (if the land be not ſtonie) can not ſhift their féete. The plough of oxen is farre better then the plough of horſes, The cauſe why? I will tell it you. The horſe doth coſt more then the oxe: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, the plough of oxen is ſo much woorth by the yeare as the plough of horſes, becauſe that the naughtineſſe of plough-men ſuffereth not the horſes to goe more then their pace. Beſides the
<pb facs="tcp:181146:22"/> ſame for the ſtayings, the plough of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhall ſtaie, when the plough of oxen ſhall goe on. And wil you ſée, how much the horſe coſteth more then the oxe, the ſame I will tell you: It is alwayes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed, that thoſe beaſtes which doe ſerue about the plough, doe lie in at the manger, betwixt Saint Lukes feaſt, &amp; holy croſſe-feaſt in May, during twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie fiue wéekes: and yet the horſe muſt be well kept to doe his daies iourney, he muſt haue oates by night, the ſixt parte of a buſhell of oates eſtéemed at a halfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penie, hee muſt haue at the laeſt twelue ſheaues of graſſe in Summer time eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wéeke, ſome horſes more and ſome leſſe, of one penie the burthen. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhoowing, if they be ſhoowed of al foure féete, the ſumme riſeth to twelue ſhillings fiue pence halpenie hy the yere, beſides the fodder and the ſtrawe: and if the oxe be in good liking to do his work, then it is needfull to allowe him at the leaſt, thrée ſheaues and a halfe of oates by the weeke, rated at one penie, and in Summer ſeaſon twelue burdens of graſſe, rated at two ſhillinges and one
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:181146:22"/> penie beſides fodder and ſtraw, and ten ſheaues of oates, doe anſwere a buſhell of oates heape meaſure. And when the horſe is olde and tired, then is there in him nothing good but the ſkinne. And when the oxe is olde, with twelue bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of graſſe, he will be woorth being fatted, or being ſolde, ſo much as he did coſt you firſt, or more.</p>
               <p>In breaking time, is a good ſeaſon for the plowma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if the ground breaketh after the plough: and the fallowing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Midſommer day, it is beſt for him whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the duſt doth riſe after the plough: and in the earing &amp; ſowing time, when the land is ſetled, and is not too cloſe: but he that hath much to doe, can not haue all the good ſeaſons. And when you do breake déepe any good land, then muſt you ſquare furrow, for to haue good reſting land: but pricke it not to déepe but ſparingly, onely doing ſo that ye may deſtroy the thiſtles &amp; the wéeds: for if the land be fallowed to déepe, and if it be wette and wateriſh when it is eared and ſowen, the plough can not then reach any certaine ground: but it
<pb facs="tcp:181146:23"/> ſhall goe flowing as in a good ground: and if the plough might goe two finger deeper then the lande was fallowed, then ſhoulde the plough finde the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine grounde, and ſhoulde bee clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſhould make faire and good plowing.</p>
               <p>In ſowing time, doe not plough large ſurrow but a little one, and well ioyned together, that the ſeede maie well fall. And if you doe plough large furrowes for to make great diſpatch, you ſhall doe hurt as I will tell you. When the land is ſowen, the harrow will come that ſhall rake all the ſéede on the hill which is betwene the ſurrowes, and the furrow which is large ſhall be diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and there ſhall grow no corne: and to ſhew you that it is ſo, when the corne is vpon the ground, go to the head of the land, and looke on the corne towardes the other head, and you ſhall ſée that the ſame which I tell you is true.</p>
               <p>If the ground be to be ſowen vpon the furrow, ſée that it be tilled with litle furrows, and the ground ſo high as you may poſſible, and ſée that the furrow,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:181146:23"/> which is betwixt the two furrowes, be ſtraight, and the land which lieth as it were a combe in that furrow, vnder the left foote after the plough, that it may be all turned, and then the furrow ſhall be ſtreight inough.</p>
               <p>Sow your lands betimes, ſo that the earth be ſetled, and the corne wel rooted before the comming of the hard winter.</p>
               <p>If perchance it happeneth that any great raine falles vpon the land with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the eight dayes, that it is ſowen, and then a harde froſt commes two or three dayes after, if the lande be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, the froſt ſhall pearce the earth ſo déepe as the water is gone in, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the corne which is ſprowted ſhal be incontinet rotten.</p>
               <p>Two perilles that are in ſowing in Lent ſeaſon ſowinges ſo betimes: The earth that is clayiſh, and the ſtony grounde, I will tell you where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: if it bee a drie ſeaſon in March, then the clayiſh earth ſhall waxe too harde, and the ſtonie grounde ſhall waxe dryer, when it is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, wherefore it needeth, that
<pb facs="tcp:181146:24"/> ſuch landes be ſowen in a conuenient time, ſo that the corne may be well nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by the moyſtneſſe of the winter. The hollow lands néed not to be ſowen otherwayes but in their time: for theſe two are two ſorts of ground which fall to be hollow and great in ſhewe, but in the ſowing of them, let the landes bee ſomewhat wet. And when your lands be ſowen: cauſe to ſcowre well the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and other wateriſh grounds, and cauſe the ditches about them to be well clenſed, that thereby your land may be the ſootter dried from the water.</p>
               <p>Cauſe to clenſe, and wéede your corne after Midſommer day, for it is not good to do it afore. And if you do cut of the thiſtles, a forte-night, or a ſeuen-night before Midſommer day, of eache ſhall come two or thrée: cauſe your corne to be wiſely reaped and put in the barne.</p>
               <p>To make the profite of your barne, ſée that you entertaine a faithfull honeſt man, that may faithfully charge the prouoſt: for it is ſéene often that the Barner, and the granetier, doe ioyne
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:181146:24"/> together to doe ill: let your prouoſt, and your granetiers cauſe the ſame corne to be truly caried, but meaſure of eight buſhels, one pecke for the waſte and decay, at the comming in, and at the going out of the barne: for their is deceite in the heaping, as I will tell you. When the prouoſt hath rendered account of the profit of the barne, then cauſe the buſhell to be proued where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall it was charged: and you ſhall finde that foure heaped quarters, ſhall make the fift, a little more or a little leſſe, and if the buſhell be narrower of fiue quarters: this take, and if it bee narrower of ſixe quarters, then take the ſeuenth: and if it be yet narrower of the ſeuen quarters, then take the eight: and yet being narrower of eight quarters, take the ninth, and of each of them a litile, either a little more or a little leſſe, according to their bigneſſe: Now ſome of theſe proffes of meaſure will render a true account but with the ninth quarter, what buſhel ſoeuer it be, either broade or narrow will do it. And if the buſhell be broade there is a great
<pb facs="tcp:181146:25"/> deceite, if the profite of your barne an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth but to the thirde of your ſeede, you get nothing except the corne be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie well ſolde: you knowe well that an acre of la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d which is ſowen with wheat, will haue three tillings, except thoſe lands the which are ſowen euery yéere, ſome more, ſome other leſſe. Each til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is woorth ſixe pence, and the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing is worth one penie: and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth to ſowe vpon euery acre two buſhels at the leaſt, and theſe two bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhels are at the leaſt woorth at Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſe twelue pence, and the wéeding a halfpenie, and the cutting downe fiue pence, and the carying in harueſt one penie, and the fodder ſhall quite the threſſhing. And the thirde part of the ſeede ought to yeelde ſixe buſhels of Wheate: And if at Michaelmaſſe Wheate bee woorth foure ſhillinges, then are ſixe buſhels woorth three ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges, and your harueſt charges doe amount to thrée ſhillings one penie and halfepenie.</p>
               <p>Chaunge euery yeare the ſeede at Michaelmaſſe: for the ſéede which is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:181146:25"/> growen vppon other lande will proue better, then the ſéede which is growen vpon the ſame land. And if you will ſée it, cauſe to till two forelandes of one and the ſame lande, and in one day, and ſowe the one with the féede that you haue bought, and the other with the ſéede which is growen vppon the ſame land: and when you come in har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt time, you ſhall proue that I tell you true.</p>
               <p>Sell not, neither ſtirre not your ſtubble, becauſe that for the leſſe you ſhould léeſe the moſt.</p>
               <p>When you cauſe dungue to be kept, with good earth, cauſe your dunguehil to be dreſſed &amp; mingled with the dungue, and cauſe euery fortenight to draw out of your ſhéepecote wherwith to dungue your clayiſh ground if you haue it, or with ſome good earth drawen out of the ditches, and then ſcatter it vpon, and if there remayne any fodder beſides the ſuſtainement of your cattell: you ſhall cauſe it to bee ſcattered with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in the yarde, and within the myre, and in your ſhéepecote alſo, cauſe it to
<pb facs="tcp:181146:26"/> be ſcattered, and in like maner in your modde, &amp; before the drought of March, cauſe all your dungue to be heaped to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, which is in the ſtables, in the yarde, and without. And when you minde to dungue your ground, and the ſame to carie, you muſt haue a man whom you truſt well, that is faithfull vnto you, to follow your cartes the firſt day, and if he ſéeth that they doe their worke without feyning, ſée at the iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes ende howe much they haue done: and let them anſwere ſo much euery day, except they may ſhewe ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine let. Your dungue which is min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with earth, you ſhall put vpon ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ground if you haue any, the cauſe wherefore I will tell you. The Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time is hote, and the dungue hote, and when the third heate is aſſembled to them, by the great heate they doe wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther away after midſommer day. The barley doth growe in a ſandie ground as you may well ſée where you goe in many places. On the Euening, the land which is mingled with dungue, cauſeth the ſand to waxe colde, and rayſeth vp
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:181146:26"/> deawe, and therefore that your landes that are ſowen may bring foorth the more, dungue them, and till them not too déepe, becauſe that the dungue is marred in turning in too déepe. How I will tell you what aduantage you ſhall haue by the ſtrawe which is mingled with the earth. If the dungue be but it ſelfe, it may laſt thrée yeares, or there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boutes, according as the land is either cold or hote. The dungue which is min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with earth, doth laſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> double, but it ſhall not be ſo quicke: you know well that the marle, laſteth more then ſtraw, why ſo? Becauſe that the dungue wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in turning it déepe into the earth, and the marle in turning of it out of the earth. And why doeth the dungue min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with earth laſt longer then the pure dungue, I will tell it to you. The dungue and the earth which are tilled together ſuſteyneth the ſtrawe that it waſteth not in the turning in, though it ſhould waſte naturally. Therefore I pray you to cauſe dungue to be kept ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the abilitie. And your dungue which is ſcattered, and ſomwhat moiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb facs="tcp:181146:27"/> is in ſeaſon good to be turned, for the ground and the dungue ſhall then take the better together. And if you put your dungue vpon fallowes, it ſhall bée all at the ſtirring turned vnder the ground, &amp; in ſowing time ſhall come vp againe, with the mingled ground: and if it be put vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtirring in ſowing time, it ſhalbe turned the more vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, and the leſſe mingled with the ground and that is not approoued: and the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer the dungue is to the ſéed it is better: at the feaſt of our Ladie, firſt cauſe to fatten your dungue, according as you haue of ſhéepe, either more or leſſe: for they do in that ſeaſon caſt much fatning.</p>
               <p>Make once in the yeare your proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, draw btwéene Eaſter and Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunday, to wit, your oxen and kine, and other cattel which are not to be kept: let them be put to fatten to graſſe, and you ſhall gaine: and knowe the certaintie that then the woorſt is better woorth then the beſt. How? I will tell it you: If they be cattell for burden, they muſt be kept better then the other and more made of, elſe the other are the more
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:181146:27"/> grieued by their default: and if you muſt buie any ſtore, buie it betwéene Eaſter and Whirſuntide: for then are cattell leane, and good cheape: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your horſes be too olde, or tyred, or leane, or of ſmall valour, you may ſell them away in due ſeaſon, and then may you relieue your ſelfe with good and young. How ſtore ſhould be kept it is good you ſhould know it, to make your ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nts wiſe: for when they ſhal ſée that you know it, they ſhall indeuor to be the better.</p>
               <p>The cattell for the plough muſt haue paſture ſufficient to doe their worke, and that they be not laboured too much vnder, when they ſhall come to the manger: for you ſhould beſtowe too much coſt to reſtore them, and ſo your gaines ſhould be diminiſhed: put them in no houſes in rainie weather: for ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting may come betwixt the haire and the ſkin, which turneth to the great da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of your cattell: and if your cattell haue their ordinarie prouender let it be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by day light, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of the hayward, or of the prouoſt, &amp; mingle it
<pb facs="tcp:181146:28"/> with a little ſtrawe of wheate, or of oates, and not of barley ſtraw, becauſe barley ſtrawe hath too many beards, which will offend the mouthes of the horſes. And why doe you ſay ſo? by proofe of the ſtraw I will tell it you: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it happeneth often that théeues doe ſteale their prouender, and the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes doe eate ſtrawe better then the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uender, and doe fatten, and doe become better. And let not much fodder be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the oxen at once, but litle at once and often, and then they eate it well, and waſte little of it: and when there is greater quantitie before them, they doe eate their bellies full, then they doe lie downe, and doe gnawe, and with the blowing of their breath, doe beginne to hate and to waſte it. And let the cattell be kept cleane, and when they be drie currie them, for that doth them good: and let the oxen be curried with a wiſpe the day, and they ſhall licke themſelues the better. Let your kine haue ſufficient paſture, leaſt they giue the leſſe milke. And when the oxe calfe is calued, let him haue his milke one whole moneth:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:181146:28"/> at the moneths ende take from him a dugge, and euery wéeke one dugge, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall he ſucke eight wéekes, and lay food before him that he may learne to eaſe: and let the cowe-calfe bee at her milke thrée wéekes: at the trée wéekes ende take away from her all the other dugs, as from the oxe-calfe, and let them haue wate and foode before them, be they within the houſe or without: for many doe die on the ground of the diſeaſe of the lights, for lacke of water. Beſides that, if there be any oxe which begins to be out of fleſh, beſtowe ſome coſt to ſuſteine him: for it is truely ſayde, that the penie is well beſtowed tha bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in two pence. If your kine be féeble, picke them out, and thoſe that be not good, put them away. And if your kine be fed in paſture of ſalt mariſh ground, then ought two kine to anſwere a ſtone of chéeſe, and halfe a gallon of butter by the wéeke: and if they be fedde in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of wood, or in medows, after mow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time, or in ſtubble, then muſt thrée kine anſwere by the wéeke, one ſtone of chéeſe, and halfe a gallon of butter:
<pb facs="tcp:181146:29"/> betwene Eaſter &amp; Michaelmaſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any replie of ſecond hay betwéene Eaſter and Michaelmaſſe, and twentie bearing ſhéepe, which are fed in paſture of ſalt mariſh ground, muſt and may well anſwere both of chéeſe and butter euen ſo as the kine aforeſaid. And if your ſhéepe be fed with freſh paſture &amp; of fallowes, thirty bearing ſhéepe ought to anſwer of butter and chéeſe, euen ſo as the kine afore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned. Now there be many great prouoſts and ſurueyors, the which will gainſay this thing, and the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherfore they do it, is becauſe that they do eat, giue &amp; waſte the white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meat: and know ye, that for to ſée if the whitemeate is not ſpent, nor otherwiſe waſted, except about the thing aforeſaid your kine &amp; ſhape may be ſo much the better, &amp; ought to anſwere the proofes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid: wil you ſée it in them how thrée kine muſt make a ſtone of chéeſe: the cow of one of theſe thrée kine ſhalbe but poore, of the which a man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not make in two dayes one chéeſe, woorth one halfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penie, which is according to the rate of thoſe daies, in ſix daies iij. chéeſes worth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:181146:29"/> thrée halfpence, &amp; the ſeuenth day of the wéeke is not in the account, becauſe that the ſeuenth day ſhal helpe for the tenth, and for the waſt, &amp; is allowed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coſt. Though it were but thrée halfepence in the weeke in xxiiij. wéekes which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Eaſter and Michaelmaſſe, there ſhalbe thrée ſhillings for the worſt cow. Now ſet downe the profite of the ſecond cow at ſo much, &amp; of the third cow euen at ſo much, then haue you ix. ſhillings, &amp; therfore you may haue a ſtone of chéeſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly to ſel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And one of the thrée kine ſhalbe but poore, of the which a man can not reape the thirde part of a pottell of butter by the wéeke, and if the gallon of butter is woorth ſixe pence, then is the third part of a pottell woorth one penie.</p>
               <p>Cauſe your hogs to be tried once in the yeare, and if you doe finde any one that is not ſound remooue it. Kéepe you neither Bore nor Sow except they be of good kind. Your other Sowes ſhall you cauſe to bee gelded if they doe not pigge: then ſhal you haue bacon made of them, euen as good as of the hog. In winter muſt you féed them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they periſh
<pb facs="tcp:181146:30"/> not, and that they may be well able to pigge: in thrée monethes they néede to be kept with good foode, to witte, in Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruarie, March and Aprill, and thrée times in the yeare, muſt your ſowes farrow pigges, except it be through ill kéeping. A nouriſhment in ſwine is to haue a long morning, and to lye drie. Cauſe your hogges to be gelded whiles they be yong, then they ſhall growe the better.</p>
               <p>Sée that your ſhéepeheard be not too haſtie, for by haſtineſſe cattel may bée to villainouſly driuen, that thereby, they may happen to periſh. When ſhéepe do goe a féeding, and the ſhéepeheard is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them to haſtie, and driuing the ſhéepe too haſtily, then is that a token that he is not gentle to his ſhéepe.</p>
               <p>Cauſe your ſhéepe to be milked eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yeare betwéene Eaſter and Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonday, and thoſe that are not to be mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, cauſe them to be ſhorne betimes, and marke them from the other, and put them in woods that bee cloſed, or within ſome other paſture grounde where they may fatten, and ſell them
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:181146:30"/> about Midſommer: for then is ſhéepes fleſh in ſeaſon, and let there wooll bee ſold by it ſelfe, with the ſkinnes of them that are dead of the morrion. And when you haue ſolde your ſhéepe, your wooll and your ſkinnes aforeſaid, ſet vp again in their ſteades ſo many ſhéepe. Some men do ſet vp againe others by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite they make of them that are dead of the morrion, howe? I wil tel you: if one ſhéepe dieth ſuddenly, they doe put the fleſh into the water, ſo long as from the morning till noone, and then do hang it vp, and when the water is dried vp, they cauſe it to be ſalted and dried: and if they doe ſée that any ſheepe beginnes to pine away, be it either that her téeth do fall, or that her téeth falles not, they cauſe them to be killed, powdred and dried as the other, and then they doe cauſe them to be preſſed, and do ſpende them at home among their men, and iourneymen, and ſo much as the priſe amounteth, they doe render in ſeaſon: and of that, and the ſkins they do ſet vp againe ſo many other ſhéepe: but I wiſh not you to doe the like. Sée that your
<pb facs="tcp:181146:31"/> ſhéepe be within at home, betweene the feaſt of Saint Martin, and Eaſter: I will not ſay but if the ground be drie, and the water be drawen to his courſe and place, and the weather be faire, that your muttons may not lie out: and let them that be kept at home haue hay, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more or leſſe, according as the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is: and cauſe to dunge the floore of the ſheepecote euery fortenight, ſo as I haue told you heretofore, and let ſtraw be laide vpon the ſame. And know ye, that you ſhall haue more profite, then if they did lie in the mire: and if your ſheepe are within in ſtormie weather, let them be by themſelues, and let them haue of the courſeſt hay, or hay mingled with wheate ſtraw, or oate ſtraw well threſhed: Wherefore, I will tell you: They are toſſed by night in the myre by ſtormie weather, and the next day after by reaſon of their lying they do not feed, and then they doe come to the cribbe hungrie, and the ſtronger do thruſt out the feeble, and do ſwallow vp without gnawing the ſmall hay, and the ſheepe that hath eaten her belly full gnaweth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:181146:31"/> her fodder, and that fodder which is not gnawen nouriſheth not, but remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth within the bodie, and therefore is vnnaturall, whereby many do periſh: and if the fodder be mingled, they will eate it the better becauſe of the courſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the fodder: and if you doe lacke hay, take the coddes and the ſtrawe of peaſon, which is good fodder for ſheepe. And when your lambes are yeaned, let the ſheepeheard take away the wooll which is about the dugges: for it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth often that the wooll ſticketh in the lambes mouth, and ſo the lambe ſwalloweth it vp: and it remaineth within their ſtomacke, and thereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are periſhed: and at the feaſt of S. Simon and Saint Iude, cauſe to draw out two of the middle ſort, and two of the beſt, and two of the woorſt, and if you doe finde that they be not ſound, cauſe the beſt of them to be ſolde, and let honeſt perſons haue them vpon good ſuretie, till hogges-day, and then cauſe other to be ſet vp againe in their ſtead.</p>
               <p>Of géeſe and hennes, let hem be at the diſcretion of the baylie, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:181146:32"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:181146:32"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:181146:33"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:181146:33"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:181146:34"/> that all the time I was a Bayliffe, both Géeſe and Hennes were let to farme, Géeſe for twelue pence, Hennes for thrée pence, and ſome for foure pence, by the yeare.</p>
               <p>Sell and buie in due ſeaſon, hauing alwaies one honeſt man or two, which may teſtifie of all things: for there bee ſome other perſons then thoſe which are accomptable, the which doo encreaſe the buyings, and doo diminiſh the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: and if any rerage runne lying vpon the finall account, let it be quickly gathered vp: and if they doo name cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein perſons which do owe the rerages: kéepe with you their names: for it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth often that Seruants and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoſtes, doo ſerue their owne turnes, and do cauſe others to ſerue their turns which they ought not: and they doo the ſame, for to hide their owne delaies. Make a view of the account, or cauſe it to be made, by ſome truſtie perſon, once in the yeare, and a finall account at the yéeres ende. The view of account muſt be made, to know the eſtate of things, as of the profits, receits, ſales, buyings,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:181146:34"/> and other expenſes. And thereupon, if there be any money remaining, take it out of the hands of the Seruants: for it happeneth often that Seruants, and Prouoſtes doo make marchandiſe by themſelues or by others, with their Lords money, to their profit, and not to the profit of their lords, the which thing is not honeſt: if you muſt buy or ſell in the countrey where is no good order: be you then well aduiſed, for you may be defrauded by them which cannot bee contraried. Thoſe that haue the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of ſuch thinges, muſt of neceſſitie haue theſe foure things: To loue and feare their Lord, and as for the raiſing of profit, they ought to doo it as though the thing were their owne: and as for their expenſes, they ſhould ſo expend, as ſuppoſing the thing not to apperteine vnto an other. There be many ſeruants and Prouoſtes which haue theſe foure things togither: but many there are which haue fled from the thrée firſt, and kéepe the fourth, and haue vſed the ſame contrary to right, as a thing appertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to an other: receiuing and taking
<pb facs="tcp:181146:35"/> with both their left &amp; right hand, when as they thinke that their delaies can be by no meanes perceiued or knowen.</p>
               <p>Viſit often your things, and cauſe them to bee viſited: for it is ſaide in a common ſaying: Who often viſiteth his owne goods, if hée gaineth not, hée dooth not léeſe: and thoſe which ſerue you by the yeare, ſhall the more beware to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ill, and ſhal endeuour themſelues the more to doo their beſt.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Here endeth Husbandry.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:181146:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
